Functions in Python are defined with that deaf keyword that we saw earlier.
It's followed by a function name, which is a lowercase
separated with underscores, and then parentheses that contain zero
or more arguments and a colon.
Everything that is indented after the function belongs to that function.
So early on in the class, if you remember, we tried to
from future import braces, and we got a no way error never going to happen.
That was a little Easter egg.
Other programming languages like JavaScript use curly braces to
delineate where is the start and end of a function.
Python does not have it. Instead, it relies on weight space.
And so going forward as we start talking about functions,
classes, if statements, you're going to have to be very mindful
of how you use white space, because if things are not
indented at the correct level, you're going to get syntax errors.
If we try to create functions that are missing some of those core components,
so if I try to create a function that does not have that colon,
I'm going to get an invalid syntax.
So, death, the name of the function, parentheses,
colon, and we'll see the Ripple shows us a helpful hint.
Once we have that colon, it's going to turn into dot, dot, dot,
prompt to say, hey, I'm expecting more input here.
In the Ripple, you can just hit a tab.
When I hit enter again, the Ripple is going to say, hey, I'm still waiting for more input.
If you're done defining your function at this point, you can just hit enter again
to get back to that three arrow prompts that we saw earlier.
And that means that the function has now been defined, and it means that I can call it.
When we are writing Python files, this extra new line after the function,
if you don't have it, it's not a syntax error, but pep 8 does state that you should have a new line
after your function definitions, just for readability sake.
You can save the output of calling a function into a variable.
I would have to change my function a little bit, so I would have to change my function to actually
return something, because if I see what is in greeting right now, it's actually going to be a
null value. The function only printed something, it's not returning any values.
So I can redefine my function and have it return a value instead of printing it.
Now when I call my function, it should return the string high, and now I can save that to a variable.
So return statements allow you to do stuff in the function and then pass those values back to the
color. You can return whatever you like. If you're going to be returning more than one value,
you can use it to pull. Now, pretty straightforward calling functions with no arguments.
How do we start making functions that do accept arguments?
We define what arguments we want to accept by separating them with commas,
separating the names that we expect them to be with commas in deeper emphasis.
And then we can use them in our function.
If we wanted to store the value of this, that would be pretty straightforward.
Now result is an integer with 30. We can also have optional arguments and provide a default value for them.
So you would not want to write a function like this in production. Your co-workers would be mad at you.
It is a mystery function that does some weird stuff. But just for the sake of example,
now I can still add my numbers. Let's say 35. I'm actually going to get nine
because there is this default value in z that is one. But I can also pass in my own value for it.
These arguments must be provided because they don't have defaults, providing these arguments is optional.
And they need to be in this specific order.
Required arguments need to be defined first. Optional arguments need to be defined last.
If you mix up the order of these, you're going to get errors.
And it's pretty helpful error. It's a syntax error, not non-default argument,
follows default argument. One more thing about functions is that here we define them
exactly in the order of the, as they were defined in the function. If you provided labels for these,
when you call the function, you can pass, you can pass those in in any order you would like.
So looking at the add numbers function here, I could call add numbers one two and three.
Or I could say that y equals one z equals two and x equals three. And because I've helped
Python out and told it, hey, I'm not calling these in order, but I am giving you the labels.
It's able to figure out what your intent was. Does that make sense?
Okay, cool. Now, we talked about default arguments. We talked about order.
Um, if we try to call a function without all of its default arguments, we're going to get
an exception. So for add numbers, I have two arguments that need to have values x and y.
If I try to call this function with only one value, I'm going to get a pretty helpful error.
It's a type error. It says add numbers is missing one required positional argument of y.
Right? Because I passed an value for this, but not for this. And Python doesn't have a default
value for it. Doesn't know what to do.
If you have arguments that have default values for everything, you can then pass in none of them.
Or some of them. Or all of them. You can mix and match. So we saw we had a create query method.
And I can say that the language is JavaScript by default. And the number of stars is
10 by default. And the sort order is descending by default.
And this is just going to return an epsilon. That says our language is language and
numbers stars is numbers stars and sort is sort.
Now when I call this with no arguments, I get JavaScript. Or I can just provide the language
or I can just provide the number of stars or any mix of them.